你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到PWN学院
welcome back to pwn college
我是Yan
I'm Yan
今天我们将继续讨论内存损坏问题
and today we're pushing on on the causes of corruption style memory errors
我们在上个视频中讨论了经典的缓冲区溢出漏洞
we talked in last video about classic buffer overflows
这集视频开始讲符号混淆
this video we'll start with signedness mixups
看看我们能讲到哪里
and see how far we go
好的，正如前面讲的缓冲区溢出的例子
all right as we saw in the previous example with a classic buffer overflow
实际上就是小缓冲区却从输入中读取大量数据的的情况
there's really just a case of a small buffer large read from user input
这是一个容易犯的错误
that's a simple mistake to make
假设你是一个开发人员想写出安全的代码
so let's say you're a developer that wants to actually make something secure
您可以在程序中进行大小检查
you might create a program that makes a check that has a size
可以先让用户输入大小
you read in the size of the user input from the user
然后检查实际输入的值的大小是否太大
then you actually check if the size is is too big
如果太大就退出
exit if it's too big
否则你就读取用户指定大小的输入
otherwise you read the input of that size
这怎么会出错呢？
so how can this be wrong
由于很微妙的原因，这确实会出错
well this is wrong for a very subtle reason
原因是标准C库使用无符号整数来指定大小
the subtle reason is that the standard C library uses unsigned integers to specify size
read、memcmp、strcmp
so the argument of read memcmp strcmp
所有这些的大小参数
the size arguments of all of these
还有很多其他类型被指定为伪类型，称为
and a lot of others are specified as a pseudotype called
如果我们查一下手册页
if we look up the man page
叫size_t. size_t是一个无符号整数
called size_t size_t is an unsigned integer
但是默认的整数类型int、short、long等都是有符号整数
but the default integer types shortened long et cetera are signed
这就产生了问题
and this causes problems
为什么有问题？回忆一下补码
why do the cause problems well recall two's complement
在补码中
in two's complement
如果你不记得补码是什么
and if you don't remember what two's complement is
或者你不能立刻想起它的含义
or don't immediately see the implications in your mind
我会回去重新看pwn大学的汇编基础课程
I would go back and rewatch the assembly fundamental lecture in pwn college
有符号和无符号变量的补码编码方式是一致的
but two's complement basically encodes signed and unsigned variables  in almost the same way
具体是有符号还是无符号取决于如何使用
and it really just depends on how you are using these variables to or these values
看你用的是有符号还是无符号
whether you're using them in a signed or an unsigned way
但实际的存储值是一样的
but the actual storage is fairly the same
所以0,12，等等
so 0 1 2 et cetera
正数和补码
positive numbers and two's complement
在一定界限下有符号整数和无符号整数的解析是一样的
up until some limit are the same between signed and unsigned interpretations
开始变得危险的是负数的情况
but where things start getting dicey is in the negative number
比如- 1的补码
so negative 1 stored in 2's complement
等于32位整数的最大值
is equal to whatever the maximum sort of view of a 32 bit integer
它等于2的32次方-1
it's equal to two to the 32-1
就是0x f f f f f f f f
and that is this ox f f f f f f f
2的32次方-2
two to the 32-2
这个f f f e等于-2，等等
this f f f f e is -2 and so on
所以补码基本上是用
so two's complement is basically a way to
一些最大的整数来表示负数
overlap the very highest value numbers unsigned with negative numbers in the signed world
这些数字的符号
and the signedness of these numbers only really
在条件跳转期间非常重要
mostly matters during conditional jumps
让我给你们举个例子
let me give you an example
在这个具体案例中
in this specific case
我们正在检查一个输入的大小是否大于16
we're checking if a size is greater than 16
如果它大于16
and if it's greater than 16
这在汇编中
this in assembly
将导致跳转到exit指令中
this will cause some sort of a jump to happen to go to exit right
这个跳转看起来可能是的这样的
this is what that jump might look like
它可能会拿eax和16比较
it might compare EAX and 16
如果你还记得，cmp会做减法，然后设置标志寄存器中的一些标志
and if you recall comp does with subtraction then sets a bunch of flags
好的，然后
right and then
条件跳转指令去检查这些标志来决定
the conditional jumps check these flags to decide
是否应该跳转
whether that jump should be taken or not
被检查的标志决定
the flags that are checked determine
跳转是否关心符号
whether the jump cares about the sign or doesn't care about the sign
因为有的指令关心符号，有的不关心
and this is there are different instructions that care about the sign versus not
jae——当大于或等于时跳转
and Jae jump above or equal or
不好意思，这里应该用ja当大于时跳转
sorry this actually should just be jump above
因为它只是检验它是否大于
because it's just checking if it's greater than
但这不影响理解
um but you get the idea
（jae）不关心符号
does not care about the sign
英文above指的大于是不考虑符号的
above means an unsigned greater than
这就是为什么用above表示无符号大于
that's how they call unsign greater than is above
这是一个无符号比较
um it's an unsigned comparison
这意味着如果EAX是0xffffffff
this means that if EAX is 0xffffffff
这里的比较结果是：0xffffffff是大于16的
the condition that this jump will be predicated on is essentially that 0xffffffff is greater than 16
这不是程序的本意
and it's not it is right
但它会执行这个跳转
and it will take that jump
0xffffffff是一个非常大的数字
that's a very large number
是肯定会跳转的
that jump will be taken
相反
on the other hand
如果跳转指令使用的是JGE
if the jump used is JGE
当大于或等于的跳跃
jump of greater than or equal to
这是JAE的有符号版
that is a signed version of JAE
它检查CMP设置的（和jae检查的）不同标志
that checks different flags that are set by cmp
CMP设置的标志还是那些
cmp still sets the same flags
（cmp）它不管数据是有符号还是无符号
it doesn't matter if that data is signed or unsigned
JGE会检查CMP设置的（和jae检查的）不同标志
but JGE will check different parts of the flags that are set
而且
and
FFFFFFF和16的比较
a comparison of fffffff and 16
从语义上讲，会检查- 1是否大于16。- 1小于16。
will result in semanticly speaking checking at negative one is greater than 16. negative one is less than 16.
不会发生跳转。所以不会退出。即使传给read的大小真是非常非常大的0xffffffff
that jump will not be taken. so the exit will not occur. eventhough the size is past to read is 0xffffffff,which is very very large.
好，我们来看看这段代码中使用了哪个
all right let's see which one is used in this code
这对这个项目的安全性意味着什么
and the implication of that to the security of this program
所以我在signedness.c中写了这个例子
so I wrote that example in a signedness.c here
很简单，就像你们记得的那样
fairly straightforward as you remember
我们来编译一下
so let's compile it
同样，我不会使用栈保护器
and again I'm gonna use no stack protector
我们会讲到这意味着什么等等
and we'll talk about what this means and and so forth
然后我
and then I
-o signedness signedness.c
dash o signedness signedness.c
我们将在本模块后面的课程中讨论这个标志
so we'll talk about this flag in a later lecture in this module
现在我们先忍一忍吧
for now let's just bear with it
如果你执行signedness
so if you execute the signedness
它会读取大小，然后
it asks of course it reads in the size and then
如果我们用strace看一下
if we just strace it
我们可以看到，如果我输入10
we see that if I read in 10
然后它会从我的输入中读入10字节
then it'll read in 10 from my input right
如果我提供10作为大小，它会读入10字节
if I provide 10 as my size it'll read 10
如果我提供一个大于10的值
if I provide something bigger than 10
它以退出代码1退出
it exits with an exit code 1
我们怎么才能骗过它呢
so how can we fool this
当然，就像我一直说的
well of course as I've been saying
我们给它0xffffffff
we just give it 0x FFFF FFFF
我当然可以把它打出来
I can of course type that out
我可以输入0xffffffff
I can do 0xffffffff
我不太确定
I don't I'm not actually sure about that
但输入-1是肯定没错的
but I can always put negative one
这实际上会把0xFFFFFFFF写到有符号size变量中
this actually will write ox F F F F F F F into my signed size
因为它是有符号整型。但这并不总有效。
because it's an signed int and this doesn't always work.
大量的读取，我们做的是读取0xffffffff。这并不总是成功的。
gigantic reads, so what we doing is  doing read of 0xffffffff. That doesn't always succed.
在内核中有特定的条件判断会让读取失败。
There are curtain conditions in the kernel where it will fail.
在调试器中它总是会失败。
in fact it will always fail in the debugger.
但在这种情况，如果我输入一堆a，它就成功了，我得到了一个段错误
but in this case it succeds if i just put a bunch of As, we see that I got a seg fault
如果我在内核日志中查看发生了什么
if I look in my kernel log for what happened
实际上，让我们
it well actually let's
我们在GDB中做这个
let's do this in GDB but
我们必须要小心一点
we have to be a little bit careful
我们来抓read和
so let's catch read and
捕获系统调用读取
catch syscall read
抱歉，gdb ./signedness
sorry GDB of the  signedness
捕获系统调用read
catch syscall read
好吧
alright
我们运行，它开始第一次read
we run so this got 1st read
这是恼人的（还没输size就退了）
that's annoying
好吧，我回来了，很抱歉
all right I'm back sorry about that
我暂停了视频
I paused the video
弄清楚发生了什么
and figured out what was going on
基本上是由于我使用的GDB catch point
basically I was using a catch point in GDB
它用于系统调用，类似于断点
is like a break point for system calls
这很棘手
it's very tricky
当catch点被触发时，某些系统调用会表现得非常糟糕
there are certain system calls that act very badly when this occurs all right
嗯
um
当我启动了signedness后发生了什么
what happened when we launched this signedness
如果我们代入- 1
right if we and put negative one
然后我们输入一堆a，它就崩溃了
and then we put in a bunch of A's and it's crash right
当然我们知道发生了什么
of course we know that what is happening is that
这个检查没有做开发人员认为它会做的事情
this check is not doing what the developer us thought it would do
- 1被解释为0xffffffff
it is negative one as being interpreted as 0xffffffff
或者说- 1存储为0xffffffff
or negative one is stored as oxffffffff
它仍然被解释为- 1，如果C认为这是符号比较
that is still interpreted as negative one because C sees this as a sign comparison
我通过反汇编这个程序来证明
let me prove this to you by disassembling this binary
如果我们找到main的位置
and if we go up to where main is
我们可以看到对比和结果
and we see the comparison and the resulting
这是调用exit
so here's the call to exit
这是J L E
here is J L E
它实际上是一个小于等于跳转
it's actually a jump of less than or equal to
所以它比较了EAX和16
so it compares EAX against 16
它做了一个小于等于的有符号比较跳转
and it does a jump of less than equal to a signed comparison
符号比较中的EAX被视为- 1或者说
and EAX in a signed comparison is treated as negative one or
输入-1被解析成0xffffffff
ox f f f F when we enter negative one
但是当它后面被传递给read的第三个参数时
but when it's passed on to read later in in its 3rd argument
它是0xffffffff，它被视为一个非常非常大的数字
it is 0xffffffff which is treated as a very very large number
很酷，所以这里的东西按预期运行，然后崩溃了
cool so here things run as expected and crashed
但是当然
but of course
上一节我们讲过有填充之类的
as we discussed in last video there's padding and stuff
因此，可能需要比您预期的更多的输入字节来导致崩溃
so it might be more than you expect input bytes is necessary to crash
在gdb中，情况就不那么好了
in GDB things are not so nice
如果我在gdb中执行
in GDB if I run
做作业需要你们知道这些
and you'll need to know this for the homework
这就是为什么我要研究这个
that's why I'm going into this
如果我运行并输入- 1，它就退出了
if I run and I say negative one it just exits
为什么
why
很明显
obviously
在GDB中，符号检查没有什么不同
signedness checks aren't different in GDB
它正常退出，而不是带着错误码1退出
and it exited normally instead of exiting with an error code with error code one
让我给你们展示一下如果我以1000为例会发生什么
let me show you what happens if I for example 1000
它会以错误代码1退出
it'll exit with error code one
但输入-1时我退出时错误码为0
so I exit with error code zero
在GDB中发生的事情是一些疯狂的，我至今还没找到原因
what happens in GDB is some craziness  in that I've never actually managed to track down
导致非常大的读取
causes very large reads
读取0x FFFF FFFFF是一个非常大的读取，将会失败
and a read with 0x FFFF FFFFF is a very large read to fail
所以它失败了，然后
so it just fails and then
快乐地继续下去
happily goes on with his day
我想在strace上也是一样的
I think it will be the same in strace
如果是- 1
if I do negative one
没有，它仍然可以正常工作
nope an strace it still works right
所以你可以看到这个巨大的数字
so you can see the gigantic number
也就是2的32次方 - 1
that is two to the 32 minus one that we tried to read
不管怎样
anyways
如果我用strace
and if I strace
哦，有时候就失败了，我认为可能由于内存对齐
oh and then every once in a while  depending on memory alignment I think it does fail
这非常非常烦人
so this is very very annoying
又失败了
that failed again
也许它真的失败了
uh maybe it actually fails
哦，成功了
oh that succeeded
哈
huh
现在我们
boom and now we
当然是段错误
of course segfault
我想知道它在GDB上有时会不会成功
um I wonder if it'll succeed in GDB sometimes
看来没那么幸运
you're not getting lucky for that
不管怎样，如何在GDB中解决这个问题？
anyways how to fix this in GDB well
别忘了你在调试器中
don't forget you're in a debugger
你可以完全控制程序
you control the program completely
我写了一个简单的GDB脚本，它在读取时中断
I wrote a simple GDB script that breaks at read
简单的设置
simply sets
这是read系统调用的libc封装
and this is the read lib C wrapper for the system call
所以这里没有问题
so there's no problem breaking there
设置RDX为
sets RDX to
实际上用0xFFF来和RDX按位与
actually masks RDX with just 0xFFF
所以现在RDX的最大值是0xFFF
so the maximum that RDX can be now is 0xFFF
我发现这是一个合理的尺寸
I found that this is a reasonable size
如果我使用FFFF，那就太大了
if I do FFFF that's still too big
如果我用这个shorted_read运行GDB
and if I run GDB with this shortened read
一切正常
things work fine
好吧，我跑了
all right so I run
-1, 然后它接着读
negative one, it reads
我输入大量A
put in my A's
程序崩溃
program crashed
让我们看看崩溃的地方
let's see  where we crashed
好吧
okay
让我们看看栈的顶部是什么
and let's see what's at the top of the stack
我们现在在ret
so we currently at the ret
我们正要返回到这里
and we were about to return to this
41 41 41 41 41 41
41 41 41 41 41
我们更改了返回地址
we overroad the return address
尽管从表面上看
even though on the face of it
一眼望去
from a glance
这个程序看起来很安全
this program seemed pretty secure
我再提一个
I'm going to mention one more
原因很相似
cause of a very similar sort of of issue
不会太深入
without going too far in depth
这个原因就是整数溢出
and that cause is integer overflows
整数溢出有点类似于符号混淆
integer overflows are kind of similar to signedness
事实上
in the fact
如果你有一个- 1
in the sense that if you have a negative one
加上1得到0
and you add one to it you have a 0
同样- 1也等于
in the same way negative one is equivalent to
0xffffffff 32位整数可以存储的最高数字
the highest number 0xffffffff 32 bit integer can store
而且
and
如果加1
if you add one to it
这就变成了零
that becomes zero
我们来看看
so let's see
在这个程序中会发生什么
what happens in the context of this program
这个程序使用了一个新函数
this program uses a new function
你以前可能没见过
that you might not have seen before
叫alloca
called alloca
Alloca只是在栈上分配空间
alloca simply allocates space on the stack
它用于动态大小的空间
it is for dynamically sized space
如果你用man alloca
so if you do man alloca
你可以看到你给它一个大小
you can see you just pass it a size
顺便说一下，这个大小是无符号的
and this size is unsigned by the way
类似于前一个
similar to the previous one
所以这里也可能有符号混淆
so there could be signedness mixups here as well
但在这里要讲的问题是整数溢出
but in this specific case the problem is  an integer overflow
如果你看这里发生了什么
and if you look at what happens here
这个程序尝试以空标识输入的终止
this program tries to null terminate the input
它所做的是从用户那里读取大小
so what it does is it reads the size from the user
它在栈上分配size + 1
it allocates size plus one on the stack
它从用户那里读取大小字节
and it reads in size bytes from the user
然后写入用户输入的东西
and then write it then whatever the user put in
在用null终止它
it nul terminates
这是一种非常常见的模式，读入字符串然后以null结尾
this is a very common pattern to read in a string and null terminated
对，但在这种情况下，这个大小加1有问题
right but in this case this size plus one has problems
INT是一个32位整数
so consider INT is a 32 bit integer
这个整数能取的最大值是多少
what's the maximum value that this integer can take
当然最大值是2的32次方-1
of course the maximum value is two to the 32-1
ox FF FF FF FF 4字节都是1
ox FF FF FF FF 4 bytes all ones
当你增加它时会发生什么
and what happens when you increment that
它会回滚成零
is it rolls back around to zero
这被称为整数溢出
this is called an integer overflow
同样的方法，如果你有一个0，然后减去1
the same way if you have a 0 and you subtract one to it
你得到oxf FFF
you get oxf FFF
这就是补码的工作原理
this is actually how 2's complement works
当你把这些解释为有符号数字时
when you interpret these as sign numbers
这是完全有道理的
this makes absolute sense
这就是补码的优美之处
right this is the beauty of two's complement that
它智能地使用了整数溢出
it uses integer overflow intelligently
但这在安全领域给我们带来了一个问题
but this causes a problem for us in the security realm in this case
因为如果我在这里输入- 1
because if I enter negative 1 here
这里执行size + 1
and this does size plus 1
这个alloca将分配0字节
this alloca will allocate the zero byte
然后
and then
我将读取0x F F F F F字节到栈
I will read 0x F F F F F F bytes onto the stack
当然，所有的东西都会爆炸，这很酷
and of course everything will explode which is awesome to see
不管怎样，这都是个问题
and this is a problem despite any
这里没有什么符号混淆之类的
there's no signedness mix up or anything
所有都是无符号的
everything is unsigned
这个size可能是一个无符号整型
this is probably an unsigned INT size
它和size_t是一样的
it's the same as size_t
我们来看看
so let's take a look at
实践中会发生什么
what happens in practice
我创建了另一个
I created another
将其写入另一个程序int_overflow
wrote this into another program int_overflow
我们来编译一下
let's compile that
好的，我启动它
alright and I launch it
它告诉我，它当然要等待用户输入大小
and it tells me of course it waits for the size
我输入一个- 1
I put a negative one
然后我输入一堆a
then I put in a bunch of A's
然后崩溃了
and it crashed
好吧，GDB也是一样
all right same sort of thing with GDB
我当然还要用shorted_read
I of course have to shorten that read
来执行整数溢出
do the INT overflow
执行，输入- 1
I run it put in a negative one
输入一堆a
put in a bunch of A's
Ops，我们看看现在在哪条指令
ops let's see what instruction we're at
啊，看，我写了太多A了
ah see I put in I think too many A's
它实际上在空处崩溃了
and it actually crashed at the null termination
这很有趣
which is interesting
让我们再运行一遍
let's run it again
- 1，我会少放一些A
negative one and I'll put in fewer A's
崩溃地址还一样
same address for the crash
输入更少的A
put in even fewer As
现在发生了什么
now what's going on
输入更少的A
putting even fewer As
为什么会崩溃哦
why is it crash oh
哈哈哈
hahahaha
你发现在哪里崩溃了吗
do you see where it's crashing
在这里崩溃了
it is crashing here
因为我们在写
because we are writing something
我们在把这里的0往这里写
we are writing this zero here
这个目标地址在
and this zero is based on
缓冲区的地址加上输入的字节数
the address of the buffer plus the amount of bytes read
因此，我们显然覆盖了保存缓冲区地址的局部栈变量
so we apparently overwrote whatever local stacky variable was holding the address of the buffer
然后崩溃了
and crash
但正如你所看到的，根据代码我们有一个缓冲区溢出
but as you can see we have a buffer overflow where according to the code
粗略的看，应该是没有的
just glancing at the code there shouldn't be one
对，但因为整数溢出导致存在一个缓冲区溢出
right but there is one because of a integer overflow
很酷
cool
我想还有一个我想说的
I think there's one more that I want to talk about
非常相似，我简单提一下
very similar I'll just mention it briefly
off by one错误
off by one errors
考虑下面的情况
consider the following consider that
从0开始的索引数组
the index array starting at zero
通常是由于某种计算错误
and oftentimes due to whatever miscalculation
或者出现了应该使用小于等于却用了小于的错误
or just an error like using a less than or equal to instead of a less than
我们将访问数组的末尾
we will access the end of the array
我们认为是数组的尽头
what we think is the end of the array
但实际上在那之后是1字节
but it'll actually be one after that
如果你有一个有三个元素的数组
so if you have an array with three elements
1 2和3，你访问的数组索引是3
1 2 and three and you access array indexed three
实际这是数组的第4个元素
that is the 4th element of the array
严格来说，这是一个off by one的错误
that is technically on off by one error
这些off by one错误会导致小的溢出
and these off by one errors can cause small overflows
而且这些小的溢出也会造成问题
and these small overflows can be problematic as well
我们很快就会讲到
as you'll as we'll talk about shortly
你们也会在作业中发现
and as you'll discover in your homework
好吧
all right
这就是这个视频的内容
that's then of this video
看到你
see you
下一个视频
next videos